We're looking at the
perfection of giving, and it's very important,
especially for your
Diamond Way vows. This is related to one
of the five Buddha families
called Ratara, which is the
southern family and is generally connected with the
color
yellow. There are four ways of giving. It's meant to
be here
just to plant a seed in your
mind, and later, when you take your
Diamond Way vows, then
you make a
commitment. But anyway, it's so you can
start
preparing. First, it's easy to give
material things, give money, give
coffee.
Okay, the second type of giving you can
give is
protection. And the names are secret.
The names of the four ways of giving
are secret. And in this case, it means
equanimity. It doesn't mean protecting people; it
means treating people
equally. I think in my
life, there are
many people of different
races, different countries, and
different genders, and for me,
it's
difficult to deal with people
who think differently about
politics. I struggle to
treat them equally, but I'm not kidding. I think we
all have different prejudices,
and it's important to know that you have
prejudices, but the ones you have to be
careful about—in my case, or well, maybe many
people on the Dharma as well.  It's
prejudice against other people
who have different ways of thinking.
So if you're going to follow the
Diamond path and if you're going to keep the
Rara vows, it's part of this: accepting
people who have different points of view,
equanimity. The third type of
giving, for Rara, is giving,
giving, and it can be in a conversation, in a
truck, for
example. And in the vows, you're supposed to
give love. The fourth type of giving
is love, but it
also covers not getting angry and it
also covers
speaking the truth to people.
These are the different types of
giving. When we talk about the perfection of
giving, of sharing, there's a
different level. When you reach the
Diamond path, and it has to do with
Rara, you're going to learn more about this
later. I'm just planting the
seeds. Four types of giving, and they're not what they seem, they're
not what they sound like.
Let's go back to the
text. This means helping
people in need. And we
had
a prison project here, and we
used to go to prisons a lot. There's
a prison in North
Tucson, and we had a center in Phoenix.
So it was easy to go to the prison. Now,
getting to the prison from  Where we
live it's about an 8-hour drive and we do
n't do it as much as we used to,
but we still have teachers who are
doing it. And here he makes a
specific and special point talking about the
people in prison because he says they
are suffering in a very
special way, and America has this problem
worse than other places. Here we have the
largest prison population.
Here he is saying that it's a very
special kind of karma, good karma, to help
the people who are in
prison. The person who was in charge
had cancer and died. So we haven't
done much, but it's a very
special kind of virtuoso work
with the prisoners. People are
very grateful, people are
very kind. The
prison directors loved our
group because the fights in the prison
decreased a lot. I'm going to show you some
pictures
tomorrow,
and some of the people who
graduated from prison have very
good businesses now.
One of them has a beauty salon and is doing
well. Here he
is talking about the danger, for
example, in Tibet it was like people being
taken to the river. In the
modern world, I think it's like
accidents.
Motorists, if no one else is
stopping, sometimes the police get angry if
you stop, but if you're the first person
there, you stop and get out to
help. If you see an accident, and once
I arrived at Shana Airport and had to
drive somewhere else, and I was going to rent
a car, and it was quite a challenge.
But there was a car in front of me, and in
Iceland, all the
fields have stones in them, and they
make walls everywhere. So
all the roads have
stone walls, and I was following this car,
and it started hitting the
stone wall, and finally it crashed. I stopped, I ran
there, and there were four
Catholic nuns in the
car, and I was asking them, "Are you okay?" And they were saying, "We
have to go to the hospital," and I
put them in my
car. I thought it was crazy because they didn't
know I was a Buddha, a
Buddhist monk, taking them to the hospital. But if
you're the first person who sees the
accident, stop and help people. It's
part of it, it's another way of
perfecting giving, giving protection, and
this is part of Ratara once you
commit to the Diamond Way,
once you take  The Diamond Way says that
one of the
best gifts you can give
is protection.
In
Buddhism, during the summer retreat of monks
and nuns, which is supposed to last two or
three months, we
stay in retreat. One of the reasons for this
is
because there are more insects.
You can kill them if you're walking around,
and it's a tradition for monks and nuns to go on
retreat and not walk around so as not to kill
the
insects. So,
here it talks about protecting
insects from the heat and the cold. Or, if you see an
insect
struggling, it says, "
Look, you can save an insect with a
flick of your
wrist. Just put your hand in the water
and pull it out." Don't be
lazy and think that their life isn't
important; their life is important to
them, just as your life is important to you.
So, if you have the opportunity to save
an insect,
do it. It's not saying that you have to
sit by a lake and
save insects all day, but if
you see an insect
trying to get out, just help it. Go up to it
and help it out. Help insects
as much as you can,
especially cockroaches.
Here it is.
Secretly, he's
referring to his secret vows because
giving freedom from fear is one of the
secret vows.
This means... and this is full of
tantra and it's
hidden like a
beginner's notebook, but I find it
incredible when he talks about giving
protection from fear. He doesn't
mean it has to be
from a
distance. If you have an insect on your
body that's enjoying your blood,
that's also a way of giving. I have a
teacher who said he liked to
feed mosquitoes. I
personally can't do it, and by the way, it
's dangerous in
Arizona because they have diseases and
this kind of thing, and you don't have to do
this.
But anyway, when you have the opportunity
to save any creature,
save it. Don't be lazy. You can be that
insect in the next
life. Remember
this. Here's something incredible
my other one taught me.
You can buy this on Amazon, and it's
cheap, and it's also made
of cheap stuff. It's for
catching insects. And we catch
insects in jars,
like
moths. I don't know, I've been
catching moths for like 30 years,
and
then they showed me this because the jar
is a lot of
work. My record is 20 in one day, my
record in one jar.  There are
three. But this is a
vacuum cleaner. So if you see a
spider or an insect, it has a battery,
and you turn it on, and then it sucks up the
insect and doesn't hurt it because it has a
special net, but it catches it. And then you take it out
and turn it off, and then they
can come out. I think it's incredible. I loved it. It
sounds like a
vacuum cleaner, and it's much faster than a
jar. It also works
better. Sometimes when you try to
catch them in a jar, you hurt them, and it's
fun. You feel like you're on a
safari. I recommend
saving an insect. Do it, go for
it. When you're doing...
sorry, when you're doing... when you're doing...
and you're giving someone
your breath, you're giving them your
happiness. This is also the perception
of giving. Just
doing it in your
imagination is the perfection of giving. You don't
have to give $100 or $1,000, just
give them your
breath, and this is the perfection of
giving. I like this
meditation image. I worked in Manhattan for about
12 years, and I used to go to the
highest parts of a building and meditate there. It
was incredible.
When I had time to eat or something, I would do
my meditation, and it's
a very
beautiful practice, the best practice.  My secret when you
're working in
Manhattan is
talking to the Buddha from the
bathroom. I'm going to teach you my
secret meditation. It's hard to find time to
meditate when you're working in a
busy office, and I used to work in
an office, it was crazy. And there was no
time to do my
prayers, so I would go to the bathroom,
close the
door and the toilet lid, and
sit there. I would sit there for five
minutes. I think a lot of people thought I
had stomach problems, and I was just doing
my business. I would just sit there doing my business. It's
a little smelly, but it's
okay, you can have privacy, nobody's going to
bother you. And I used to sit there and do
my prayers, and one day
I decided I was going to talk to my
future Buddha. And I would say, "Hey Mike," and he would say, "
What? By the way, he never
[Laughs]
answers." But I would say, "I know you can see me from the
future. You can see me, you
know, from the future. You can see me now, sitting in the
bathroom." So I would talk to him and
say, "Hi,
I hope it didn't take us too long to
become a Buddha. And if you have any
advice, I'm
listening." Because a Buddha can see the
present, past, and future. So he's
supposed to be your future version of the
Buddha.  And you can talk to him, and I think it's very
healthy. You might get taken to a
psychiatric hospital. But you can talk
to your version of the Buddha and say, "Hi, hey, I'm getting
closer. How's my
practice?" And I think it helps a lot. I
think it's a very good practice.
So just don't talk too loudly.
While in the
bathroom, I used to use that office for
many practices.
Then he's going to
quote
Bodhisattvas, and we're studying this
very famous book that was written
a year ago, and it's being translated by Master
Chantil.
If you're interested in
Sanskrit, we're studying
it. I'm teaching Sanskrit during
these
classes. So he's going to
quote Bodhisattvas, and that's how
we learn. And there's a very
interesting discussion in the book. And this is the
discussion:
giving a
perfection. What is the Sanskrit for
perfection? Say
param. Americans say "paramita,"
but it means something that went away,
and the word "going away" in English comes
from "ita," so it means to go away. "Para"
means the other side of the
ocean, like swimming from San Diego to Kyoto or
something like that. This is
paramita. And then he says it's the act of
giving a
paramita. And
yes, and no, it's paramita.
The six perfections are not
perfections; the six perfections
lead you to perfection. The word "
perfection" is a
famous mistake. It's not that what you are giving
is perfect. It's that giving will make you
perfect. We call it "
paraita," but it's actually "paraita
parador." So here it
says, "Dana paramita" is the
perfection of giving, the perfection of giving. And we
say, "Yes, of course, the Buddha taught the
perfection of giving." And then someone says, "It's
not the perfection of giving," and we say, "
Why?" And they say, "There are still poor people. There are
still poor people." The Buddha lived on
this planet. Yes, the Buddha achieved, managed to
become a Buddha. I suppose the Buddha
did the six perfections. Yes, the Buddha
perfected perfection number one.
Yes, the Buddha perfected giving. Yes, so
why are there still poor people?" And it
says, "Then we have to talk. What does it
mean to perfect
giving? It's
not about eliminating and eradicating
the people who are
poor. The perfection of giving doesn't mean
that there are no more poor people; it means
that you want to try. You have the
motivation to always try to help them.
Why is it that there are still poor people?"
Poor people, if the Buddha is someone who gives, who
masters perfection, why are there
poor people? This comes from your side. The
Buddha can't fix your seeds. The
Buddha can't give you money seeds.
You have to generate your own
money seeds. The Buddha's giving is perfect,
but you didn't
hear it. Your seeds are your seeds.
In fact, you want to hear something incredible? I ca
n't give you
anything. When Grandpa gives you money, who
gave it to you? You gave yourself
100. By
the way, Alo, I think he's
donating to the families of someone who
died this week. So
you have to understand what
perfection is. Giving, and you can be perfect
in your way of giving, and there will still be
poor people. And you can't really
protect the insect. If they have the
seeds, you're going to protect them, and if they don't
have the seeds, when you try to
save them, you're going to kill them, you're going to drown them.
You know, if you want to save a
water bug, sometimes you end up
killing them. So perfection isn't
that you
protect them; perfection is that you want to
protect them. You have to understand what
this desire to do is in
Buddhism. When you're trying to help
other people, you're limited by
their seeds, and you have to
get used to this. Otherwise, you're
going to...  You're going
to get discouraged and you're going to say, "Oh, I
tried to help three people and they got mad
and told me to
leave, okay?"
And that's okay. You're still giving, you're
having this desire to help, and you can't
control the results of your
practice. You can't do that when you're
trying to help other people. You can't
control what's going to happen,
but you have to try. Of course,
you have to try your best.
Of course,
everything is always going to be alright. We
have a lot of problems here at Diamond
Mountain. We just spent 20 years being
able to offer people a
space where they can retreat. Twenty
years of hard work, and there are people who have a
good time and there are people who don't.
And it's like, "I'm so sorry, I
'm just trying to give you a
space to get away from your phone.
I'm not trying to do anything wrong.
I'm just trying to help you." So you can't
control what happens, which
means that when you're in the
business, in the business of
Bodis, you can't discourage Bodis. It's like,
foolish, you try to help someone and they
're not happy, and you tell them, "I'm sorry, I
'm not happy. Do the same thing tomorrow."  I can't
keep trying to make you happy.
Nobody can
make another person happy. It's not possible. You can't. It
depends on their seeds. But
your responsibility as a bodhisattva is to
do your best and try to make them
happy. And this means you should
never discourage them. You can't
control what
happens with your good deeds. You can't
control it. Don't leave Diamond because
someone had a
bad time. That doesn't make sense. This doesn't
make sense. You do your best,
you do your greatest effort to help
others, and if their seeds are different, they're
going to have a
terrible time. And then you have to be patient.
After this, don't make bad seeds.
From your bad
seeds, say, "Oh, I'm so sorry you didn't
enjoy Diamond. We'll try to get you
a pool next year. I'm sorry you did
n't like the food. I'm sorry you
met a
snake. I'm sorry, we'll
ask the
snake if it can go somewhere else."
You can't control everything, and a Buddhist
should have a sense of humor
about their practice. If you made a mistake today,
yes, you're going to go home and give up. I'm
not going to mess it up again
tomorrow. And this is a  Bodis, don't
be so serious about it. You can't
control the seeds other
people have. Okay, and they're going
to criticize you. You're going to give them money,
you're going to give them time, and then people
say, "I don't like the food, I don't like
the food. Next time you should
have better food."
And when you're in the business of
bisas, you can't listen to the
customer. No, no, no, don't go crazy. Just keep
helping them. Stay silent and
keep
helping. Shut up and keep
helping. And maybe some people
will thank you, and other people will speak
ill of you. But what else are you going to do? Are you going
to quit? Are you going to go watch Netflix?
That's fine. I like
Netflix. I
like Korean comedies, but then
I get bored in like an
hour, and then you have to go back and do a...
This is the best
business. You can't measure the success of
Lord
Buddha by the economic level
of the country. It's not connected. It depends
on the seeds of the people who live in
that country. You can't judge Lord
Buddha. You can't judge bisas by the
economy of the country. It's crazy. They didn't
create the economy; you're creating it.
They're just trying to say, "How to
change it?"
If the judge  The success of a
Buddhist practice is that it changes the world
for other people who don't practice.
So this is
crazy. Even
practitioners don't
limit themselves to giving to non-
Bodhis. There are people who aren't
Bises, and you can't
judge them by the economics around
them. I had a friend, a Christian friend. I
think I told you this story. I went on a
retreat for three weeks, and I have a
Christian friend. We grew up together. We were eight
years old when we
met,
and I invited him to come and be with me.
He came from Phoenix to Florida, and we had
a very interesting conversation. He's
a very good Christian, and I used to go to his
church for fun
because they had better
Bible studies than my church. I would skip classes to
study the Bible at his
church when I was a kid, and we had
very long conversations.
But something disturbed me. He said, "This thing
about Bodhis disturbs me," and I asked him
why. He said, "So, in
theory, Bodhisattvas plant
seeds and live in a bubble, a
beautiful bubble. Their life is going to be very
happy and beautiful, and all the people around them
are
suffering. So, in your religion, you say
that Bodhisattvas collect good things."
seeds and that guy lives in a
rough paradise in
FL and all the other people in
FL are suffering and he told me, "I do
n't like that idea, what's your
idea?" And well, we
started talking about weird stuff
like someone there making you suffer,
someone
created you, and then someone also caused you to get
cancer. And I'm like, this is a better bubble
than my bubble, thinking, "Someone created you and
then that person also gave you cancer."
So I
think we're in a bubble and you ca
n't get out of it. If you can
reach out and get out of your bubble and
you can give people weapons, you can
teach them to plant seeds, but you can't
control their
bubble. Of course, their bubble comes from you.
The perfection of giving is a
mental practice, not a
physical one. The motivation to share what you
have is the perfection of
giving. The circumstances and the seeds of
other people can prevent them from
receiving what you want to give them, but your
motivation and your desire to give, that's the
perfection of it. It's
not the perfection of how you give it, it's
your desire and your motivation to
give. You can give him
dollars and he spends them instead of teaching
and goes to Argentina, and I don't know, you just
have to do it.  Give the best you can,
be generous, and help people. You can't
predict what they're going to do with
it; it doesn't work that way. It
means increasing your motivation to give,
and that's the perfection of giving. You can't
control what the world is doing; you can't
control what people
do with what you give them.
You simply have to keep giving. By the way, give wisely. Don't
give people drugs; don't
give them weapons; don't give people things
that will
hurt them. You have to do your best not to
hurt anyone. I know parents who have a lot of
money and they hurt their children because they
give them everything, and those children become
people who can't do anything because you
give them everything. It's not the amount you give, it's
the wisdom behind what you give. Use
wisdom. Here it says, and it's talking to
many monks, and it
means the three parts of
the habits of a
monk who is not poor, and it tells you that you
need...  You have to be ready
to give something to someone. Being ready
is also the perfection of giving. The monk should
give his habits to
someone, and they say, "No, you shouldn't do that."
And I did it once because we
were on a hike and someone
was very cold.
But generally, you shouldn't give away your
habits, but you should have the
motivation and the desire to give. "Do you
want to give me your habits?" And you say, "Yes, it's
appropriate that you do so."
This means start
small and give things that are
easy. Share vegetables.
Yesterday I was giving someone
vegetables; they kept going back to the
plate. They say, "Start with
small things," and it's about learning to give
people small things, and from there you can
start building to bigger things.
Start with
small things. If you start with
small things, in the end you will have the
capacity to give even your body.
Start with small things. Give
small things all
day, and in time you will be able to give
even your
body. You can increase your
generosity by sharing and start by
sharing small things
constantly. But small things.
Next picture, I think it's a
dead person. It's difficult to find a picture of
a dead person online. People don't
like it. People don't want to see
this. We are all going to die. We all
have to die.
Everything you have  You're going to
leave it?
I had this amazing ring with a
diamond in my bag and I carried it everywhere,
and yesterday someone was telling me
about their 10-year-old son, and I
thought I should give him the
diamond ring, and I gave it to him, and then I started
regretting giving it to him, and maybe
my wife is going to be mad, but then I
thought, what if I keep it? Anyway, I can't keep it; in the
end, it's going to be
in a bag when I die, and then
Rob is going to have to clean that bag, and someone else is going to have it, someone else is going to have it,
and I said, I'd better keep the credit.
So I'd better give it away before I die. I do
n't know, when I see things like that, still in my
bag, give it to someone else. We don't know,
maybe we'll be in an
accident. So I'd better give it to
someone before it's too
late. When you
die, you can't take anything with you.
Do something nice before it's too
late and someone else is going to give it away.
And by the way,
you feel free when you give away
your things. I don't have
anything, and I already gave away all the cool stuff except that
bass, that guitar. So, just keep it
while
you can. Besides, it's terrible.  For other
people, having to clean your things is annoying. They're going to
say, "Why didn't you give this away? Now I
have to clean it." It's annoying for
other people.
The habit of traveling light through
life will make you much
happier. Get rid of the things you don't need. I have three t-shirts. If I have underwear that I have to change every day, just keep the things you really need and give away everything else. You'll feel much lighter, you'll feel happier, it will be easier for you to give and
share.
Never, ever feel satisfied with what you've already
given. Keep giving and
giving and
giving. If someone asks you for
something, give it to them,
keep giving.
Now we have some tips on
how to
give. The fine print in the
contract: if you don't have anything to give and you
're tempted to make some money in a
dishonest way,
forget it. Don't think, "I'm a
B. I need to make...
Ah, maybe I
can cheat the IRS and that way I can give more."
No. This isn't the perfection of
giving. It doesn't count as
generosity to get something, to get something in a
dishonest way and give it away. This
is wrong. Better not to give anything at all.
Again, his
audience was monks and people
Lay people in his time had many
problems because he was
criticized a lot for teaching them. You can read
the
books; the people who criticized him have already died, but he was
criticized very harshly for
teaching them.
He says
the first three
perfections are especially
appropriate and suitable for
lay people, for those who are not monks or
nuns.
Why? It's simple: monks and nuns shouldn't
have
things. What is the second
ethical point? Lay people are
doing more business;
they have more opportunities to be ethical
in some
way.
Patience. There's a joke in the book
that if you don't live a
monastic life, you need more patience because you're going to
meet more people who
irritate you. You meet people who
irritate you a little more outside the
monastery. But there are many
inside the
monastery too. This is a quote from Entering
the
Middle Way, which is
a classic of Emptiness that I'm going to
teach you after we finish this one
in December. I
hope. It
says the first three
perfections are especially good
for
lay people. There are certain gifts you should
n't give;
the gift of your body is one of
them, losing your body and giving your life to
another.  "Person" doesn't mean like body parts. It's
okay as long as you don't
die, but dying for someone else? No, no, we don't
go to that level. We're not that
strong. So don't give more than you
're capable of. Don't give your body. You need it. There will
come a day when maybe it will be
okay for you to give your body, but
we're not there
yet. No, we're not there
yet. It's
not appropriate to give your body at this
point.
And it says you're not allowed to give and
hand over your body. You have to take care of your
body. You have a responsibility to
take good care of your body, eat well,
exercise, take care of your
body. Once you're in the
bodhisattva business, your body is already
other people's bodies. So you don't have the
right to hurt it, to overfeed it. You don't
have the right not to
exercise it. That body isn't yours anymore. You've already
dedicated it to other people. You already have
a moral responsibility to stay
healthy. When
the day comes when giving your body
will be as easy as giving
your vegetables, then you're ready. There are
people who are trying to do
these things, and the truth is they're just showing off. They
just want
other people to notice that they're capable of
cutting off a finger, and the Buddhas are going to
tell you...  Keep your fingers, take care of them, don't show off
trying to do anything bodily,
no.
Take care. We had a
person. The cool thing about being taught by your
grandfather is that I have many stories.
We were studying Milarepa
in New
Jersey when I was at the Mongolian temple,
and there was a
young man, and we studied Milarepa's life,
and Milarepa went out into the forest,
and this person, this young man,
immediately gave away all his things and went to this little
piece of forest. And he said, "I'm going to
live like Milarepa," and as soon as there was the
first cold day, he came back, and it was very funny.
Forget about those
things. I stayed in a cave once. I was going to
meditate in a cave, and at night there were
like 1,000 spiders, and I said, "I think I'm going to
go to Diamond Mountain and
stay in one of those cabins that
have a door."
Okay, okay.
And here he's going to talk about things that
are not appropriate. It's
not appropriate for a monk or nun to
give away or give away their
habits. Unless someone is
freezing to death, can I say
something? Tomorrow is today is tomorrow.
What
time can I announce it?
Okay, I don't care.
545 We're going to ordain
here and you'll find out who it is when you
come, but if you want to
see how we ordain a nun, you're
welcome to
come.
I have an opinion that if someone asks me to
ordain them, then here's my
opinion: I think an
ordained person should
stand out not because of their haircut and
not because of their clothes, but because they should
have a higher level
of integrity and morals. In my
opinion, you should be able to say, "This
person is a monk." This person is a
monk not because of their
haircut and not because of their clothes, but because they are
kinder and more
ethical. They refuse to be unethical, and I think
we should be able to identify a
monk by their ethics and their
behavior. And I think even
hair and clothes are
distracting. I think in the modern world, in
ancient times, if you saw
someone with this haircut and these
clothes, you shouldn't have
intimate relations with this person. But
in the modern world, I do
n't think it's a
distraction when a person is
wearing their habits or their haircut
is different, and I think fewer people
talk to them, and I've seen that.
Monks who look strange and nobody wants to
talk to them and they can't teach, and I think
I feel strongly that if you
ask me about ordaining someone
else, you know, I have to give my
opinion. If they don't want to, you can do it
the
traditional way. Use your hairstyle and
your... and nobody's going to talk to you. Your parents are
going to talk to you, and that's fine if you want to do that. It's
fine if you want me to do it. I'm
not selling haircuts,
and I'm not
selling... I'm
selling super moral behavior, and I
think a monk or a nun
should be known for their behavior and
not their appearance. That's what someone who is
truly ordained is. And that's the kind of
ordination I'm
offering. It's inappropriate for an
ordained person to
give away your habits, unless
someone is
literally freezing to death. Give them your clothes in
seconds. It
says it's inappropriate to give certain gifts
to monks and
nuns, for example,
food after noon,
after 12. It's inappropriate. They shouldn't
take these things. In this
tradition, in the tradition I
grew up in, when you become a
monk, they give you a choice
about whether you want to...  I stopped eating after
12 and I maintained it for 15 years. I didn't
eat anything after
noon for 15 years, and then I started
doing
yoga. I needed to eat in the
afternoon because of the yoga I was practicing.
I had to eat more, so I changed my
eating habits. But in this
tradition, in the
oldest traditions, a monk shouldn't eat after
noon. In this tradition, when you are
ordained, they give you the option, and you can
maintain it for a day or you can
maintain it for the rest of your life.
It depends on you. I generally
believe that I generally don't eat after noon anymore,
unless I have something from Diamond. I
generally don't eat after noon anymore,
and I think it's healthy. I think it's
very healthy. I think it
also helped me in my business career that I did
n't eat after noon
throughout my
business, and I didn't need to. And I think it's
very helpful to keep your mind very
clear, and I think it helps a lot, but it
depends on
you. It says that
monks,
nuns, and non-Buddhists should
n't have onions or
garlic,
therefore it would be inappropriate
to offer them garlic or onions.
They say that there are
special animals that live in the
food that  They believe in the earth. So they don't
eat onions, they don't eat
potatoes. They say you're going to kill small
creatures.
So to give something inappropriate to
another
person of another
religion is
inappropriate. This
means
smelly things. And you're, you know, in
monasteries, you're with other people,
full of people, and we're debating
for two to three hours, and it's inappropriate to eat
onions or garlic. It's difficult for everyone because of
that
stinky smell. So generally,
monks don't eat foods that are very
smelly.
Offering
something to someone with the
intention of criticizing it is not
appropriate. Giving the Diamond Sutra of the
Diamond Bearer to someone who
is
just trying to criticize it is
inappropriate. It's
a difficult expression. It's
wanting to die, and it can
mean depression.
A person wants to
commit
suicide. You
're not being a bad person. You refuse to
give them poison. You refuse to give them a gun. You
're not breaking your bad habits. If
someone tells you, "Buy me a gun, I
want to commit suicide," and you say
no, and they say, "But you're a bad person, you have to
give me what I ask for," you say no.
Okay.  It doesn't mean you have to give
everything away and it's going to hurt someone else. Don't give it away. You're
definitely not allowed to
share secret teachings with
people who aren't ready or who haven't been
initiated. I had two nightmares
this
week, and I don't remember ever having
one. I
have friends who have
nightmares every night, dreaming they're being chased,
and I never
have nightmares, but I had nightmares
this
week, and I was shocked. I was
having
nightmares about people practicing
tantra in an
inappropriate way, not following the rules of
tantra, or not following the rules for
teaching tantra. I had two
terrible nightmares, so I think you should
know the rules for sharing the
Diamond Way with other people.
If you have
secret teachings that
Grandfather gave you, Grandfather's rule is that you have to
finish your 18 courses before you can
receive them. I've tried making
exceptions, and I think they all
failed. Please don't give other
people secret teachings
until they finish their 18 courses.
This is
Grandfather's request. And please don't get things
from the internet. Not the tantric courses
here, the 18 courses here are the best.
in the world, and they are the best in
history, and I think it's like 20,000
pages. You can spend your
whole life on it. You don't need to search the internet and
find some weird, strange thing that isn't
anyone's lineage. You don't need
that. If
you finish the 20,000 pages, if you want to
learn something more, let me
know, and I'll check your assignments
first, and then I'll give you something even
stranger to study.
But don't look for things. The
Diamond Way courses
are complete, and they are the best
in the world. It's pure, it's very clean, it's
incredible. It's beautiful. It's
a beautiful, loving practice. So do
n't waste your time. Don't give me
nightmares, please. They were
terrible nightmares of a person getting lost in
hell, and it was terrible, and you don't need that,
okay?
If you get through and finish your 20,000 pages and you
're still not
satisfied, look me up, and I'll give you
something even stranger to
study. There are many things online that are not
appropriate, that are not the
Diamond Way. Everything that is authentic to the
Diamond Way, all these
authentic practices, are in the
courses.  There's nothing more to
it, and it's a lifelong practice.
You can practice your whole life and you won't even
come close to the end. You do
n't have to do other things that are
weird. Don't make me lose more
hair; it's falling out. Do
n't teach the
deeper or secret teachings to people who are
n't ready,
people for whom it's not
appropriate. I tried it, and there were
people I thought were special,
and it was a disaster. So please do it right.
Make sure they do their
18 courses. If they don't want to finish their 18
courses, then they won't do well on
the path. If they say it's too much
work, then they won't succeed on
the path of the diam. So don't do it.
Letting a criminal who can
hurt more people go free. They shouldn't
stay locked up
and have their trial. I'm not going to say anything
more. It's not kind to fix and
resolve for someone who is
dangerous. Being a bodyguard doesn't mean you're going to get
everyone out of
jail, people who can hurt
other people. If we can help them, if we
can make them better, go to the
prison, teach them,
dedicate  Your life to teach in
prisons and do it for 6 years, and
then if there are people you think
should be released, help them. We've
done this many times, but this doesn't
mean we should release
everyone from prison who might
hurt other people.
There are certain things in
life you shouldn't offer to other
people, you know, someone who wants to
kill themselves or someone who wants to do
drugs. Being a Bodis doesn't mean you give
everything; being a Bodis means you take
responsibility for giving what is
appropriate without hesitation. We have a few
more minutes. I
promise you that when I was cooking in
India, I made my students suffer
much more than
this.
And we're almost done.
Never give
anything
without the understanding that
more of it will come back to you multiplied
times. And it's not wrong to think like that. It's
okay if I give 0.00, I'm going to get 0.00. And
so I give 0.00, and that's okay.
We have 3
minutes. This is talking about the
morality of giving and making decisions
that are difficult. As a
Bodis, you sometimes have to make
Difficult decisions. You have a lot of money and
many good causes to
give to, and as a Bodhisattva, the decision of
who you give your money to is part of the
Bodhisattva lifestyle. You're
not just going to give your money away.
I was telling my teacher, "There are many
people living on the streets in New
York. I must help them." And my teacher
said, "No, do your best to
make sure you're not paying for
someone else's alcohol or drugs. Help them,
but
if you want to help a children's school,
or if
you want to do something else, you have to make
difficult decisions. We don't have unlimited funds.
You have to give everyone something,
but you have to make decisions like a
Bodhisattva. Where do you put your giving? And it's part of
making these
difficult decisions about where to donate.
This is the problem,
and you must make these decisions with
joy, with gladness, and with
decisiveness, like a surgeon who cuts
when he has to
cut. You must be decisive, and it's not
so bad to say, 'I'm going to donate to your
project, but I want to see the calculations.
I want to see the receipts.' I'm not going to donate
to someone I don't know, something that
someone who never shows up again will never give back." That's
okay.  Being
tough on what you give is your
responsibility. I'm going to donate to your
project, but I want to see the receipts.
I want to see the
calculations. I want to see the
tax payments. I want to make sure your
calculations are clean, and if they're not
clean, I want my money back, and I'm
going to give it to someone else.
Part of what he gives is that he
has to be responsible and
accountable. I'm going to
donate, but I want to make sure you
're using that money
correctly. It's
very difficult to take a
donation from a bigwig. They're
demanding; they want everything to be
right. And you have to be tough on who you
give your
money to. Last
thing: we never had...
we had 3,000 diamonds a
day, and everything was covered in
diamonds. A hand that full was a
million dollars, and we had tables
covered in diamonds.
And I would have conversations with my
coworkers, and I would say, "
Hey," they would tell me, "Mike, you have a good
heart; you trust
everyone, but don't make it easy for
people to steal because you're going to
hurt them. Not everyone is so noble
that they can just ignore it." A
Fistful of Diamonds... you have to have
systems in place.  You have to have cameras,
you have to have security doors, and
you have to have armed guards.
That's part of being a Bodhisattva. A Bodhisattva
also has to respect the
property and belongings of others. A
Bodhisattva also has to make sure it's
not easy for other people to steal
things because they'll hurt
themselves. Do you understand? A Bodhisattva also has to make sure that
others don't get
hurt. A Bodhisattva has the
responsibility to protect other
people from themselves. So when you
're in the Bodhisattva business, I learned a
lot that day, and I still think about it. I do
n't like to distrust people. I
want to put diamonds on the table, and they tell me, "No, don't do it.
There's someone who is
n't as strong as you. They're going to steal
something, and then you're going to get them into
trouble."
So a Bodhisattva shouldn't
make it easy for other people to
hurt themselves or to
not have that same kind of
control.